Let's get started with our linear algebra review.
我们先复习一下线性代数的知识
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
In this video I want to
在这段视频中
tell you what are matrices and what are vectors.
我会向大家介绍矩阵和向量的概念
A matrix is a
矩阵是指
rectangular array of numbers
由数字组成的矩形阵列
written between square brackets.
并写在方括号中间
So, for example, here is a
例如
matrix on the right, a left square bracket.
屏幕中所示的一个矩阵
And then, write in a bunch of numbers.
先写一个左括号 然后是一些数字
These could be features from
这些数字可能是
a learning problem or it could
机器学习问题的特征值
be data from somewhere else, but
也可能表示其他意思
the specific values don't matter,
不过现在不用管具体的数字
and then I'm going to close it with another right bracket on the right.
然后我用右方括号将其括起来
And so that's one matrix.
这样就得到了一个矩阵
And, here's another example of
接下来 看一下其他矩阵的例子
the matrix, let's write 3, 4, 5,6.
依次写下1 2 3 4 5 6
So matrix is just another
因此实际上矩阵
way for saying, is a
可以说是二维数组的
2D or a two dimensional array.
另一个名字
And the other piece
另外
of knowledge that we need is
我们还需要知道的是
that the dimension of the
矩阵的
matrix is going to
维度
be written as the
应该写作
number of row times the number of columns in the matrix.
矩阵的行数乘以列数
So, concretely, this example
具体到这个例子
on the left, this
看左边
has 1, 2, 3, 4
包括1 2 3 4共4行
rows and has 2 columns,
以及2列
and so this example on the
因此 这个例子是一个
left is a 4 by
4 × 2的矩阵
2 matrix -  number of rows by number of columns.
即行数乘以列数
So, four rows, two columns.
4行乘2列
This one on the right, this matrix has two rows.
右边的矩阵有两行
That's the first row, that's
这是第一行
the second row, and it has three columns.
这是第二行 此外包括三列
That's the first column, that's the
这是第一列
second column, that's the third
第二列 第三列
column So, this second
因此 我们把
matrix we say it is
这个矩阵称为一个
a 2 by 3 matrix.
2 × 3维的矩阵
So we say that the dimension of this matrix is 2 by 3.
所以我们说这个矩阵的维度是2 × 3维
Sometimes you also see this
有时候大家会发现
written out, in the case
书写有些不同
of left, you will see this
比如左边的矩阵
written out as R4 by 2
写成了R4 × 2
or concretely what people
具体而言
will sometimes say this matrix
大家会将该矩阵称作
is an element of the set R 4 by 2.
是集合R4×2的元素
So, this thing here, this
因此
just means the set of all
也就是说
matrices that of dimension
这个矩阵
4 by 2 and this thing
R4×2代表所有4×2的矩阵的集合
on the right, sometimes this is
而右边的这个矩阵
written out as a matrix that is an R 2 by 3.
有时候也写作一个R2×3的矩阵
So if you ever see, 2 by 3.
因此 如果你看到2×3
So if you ever see
如果你看到
something like this are 4 by
有些地方表达为
2 or are 2 by 3,
4×2的或者2×3的
people are just referring to
一般都是指
matrices of a specific dimension.
一个特定维度的矩阵
Next, let's talk about how
接下来 让我们来谈谈如何
to refer to specific elements of the matrix.
表达矩阵的某个特定元素
And by matrix elements, other than
这里我说矩阵元素
the matrix I just mean
而不是矩阵 我的意思是
the entries, so the numbers inside the matrix.
矩阵的条目数 也就是矩阵内部的某个数
So, in the standard notation,
所以 标准的表达是
if A is this
如果A是
matrix here, then A sub-strip
这个矩阵 那么A下标 ij
IJ is going to refer
表示的是
to the i, j entry,
i j对应的那个数字
meaning the entry in
意思是矩阵的第i行和第j列
the matrix in the ith row and jth column.
对应的那个数
So for example a1-1 is
因此 例如 A11
going to refer to the entry
表示的是第1行
in the 1st row and
第1列所对应的那个元素
the 1st column, so that's the
所以这是
first row and the first
第一行和第一列
column and so a1-1
因此A11
is going to be equal to
就等于
1, 4, 0, 2.
Another example, 8 1
另一个例子 A12
2 is going to refer to
表示的是
the entry in the first
第一行第二列
row and the second
对应的那个数
column and so A
所以A12
1 2 is going to be equal to one nine one.
将等于191
This come from a quick examples.
再看一个简单的例子
Let's see, A, oh let's
让我们来看看
say A 3 2, is going to refer
比如说A32 表达的是
to the entry in the 3rd
第3行第2列
row, and second column,
对应的那个数
right, because that's 3 2
是吧 因为这是3 2
so that's equal to 1 4 3 7.
所以这等于1437
And finally, 8 4 1
最后 A41
is going to refer to
应该等于
this one right, fourth row,
第四行第一列
first column is equal to
对应的数
1 4 7 and if,
所以是等于 147
hopefully you won't, but if
我希望你不会犯下面的错误
you were to write and say
但如果你这么写的话
well this A 4
如果你写出了A43
3, well, that refers to
这应该表示的是
the fourth row, and the
第四行第三列
third column that, you know,
而你知道
this matrix has no third
这个矩阵没有第三列
column so this is undefined,
因此这是未定义的
you know, or you can think of this as an error.
或者你可以认为这是一个错误
There's no such element as
根本就没有什么A43
8 4 3, so, you know, you
对应的元素 所以
shouldn't be referring to 8 4 3.
你不能写A43
So, the matrix
因此 矩阵
gets you a way of letting
提供了一种很好的方式
you quickly organize, index and access lots of data.
让你快速整理 索引和访问大量数据
In case I seem to be
可能你觉得 我似乎是
tossing up a lot of
介绍了很多概念
concepts, a lot of new notations
很多新的符号
very rapidly, you don't need
我讲得很快 你不需要
to memorize all of this, but
把这些都记住
on the course website where we
但在课程网站上
have posted the lecture notes,
我们已经发布了讲义
we also have all of these definitions written down.
所有这些定义都写在讲义里
So you can always refer back,
所以 你可以随时参考
you know, either to these slides,
包括这些幻灯片
possible coursework, so audible lecture
你可以随时回来观看视频
notes if you forget well, A41 was that?
如果你忘了A41到底是表示什么？
Which row, which column was that?
哪一行 哪一列是什么？
Don't worry about memorizing everything now.
所以现在不要担心记忆问题
You can always refer back to
你可以随时回来参考
the written materials on the course website, and use that as a reference.
课程网站上的材料
So that's what a matrix is.
所以 这就是矩阵的定义
Next, let's talk about what is a vector.
接下来 让我们来谈谈什么是向量
A vector turns out to be a special case of a matrix.
一个向量是一种特殊的矩阵
A vector is a matrix
向量是只有一列的
that has only 1 column so
矩阵 所以
you have an N x 1
你有一个 n×1
matrix, then that's a remember, right?
矩阵 还记得吗
N is the number of
N是行数
rows, and 1 here
而这里的1
is the number of columns, so, so
表示的是列数 所以
matrix with just one column
只有一列的矩阵
is what we call a vector.
就是我们所说的向量
So here's an example
因此 这里是一个向量的
of a vector, with I
例子 比如说
guess I have N equals four elements here.
我有 n = 4 个元素
so we also call this
所以我们也把这个称为
thing, another term for
另一个术语是
this is a four dmensional
这是一个四维的
vector, just means that
向量 也就意味着
this is a vector with four
这是一个含有
elements, with four numbers in it.
4个元素的向量
And, just as earlier
而且 前面我们讲
for matrices you saw this
矩阵的时候提到过
notation R3 by 2
这个符号R3×2
to refer to 2 by
表示的是一个3行2列的矩阵
3 matrices, for this vector
而对于这个向量
we are going to refer to this
我们也同样可以
as a vector in the set R4.
表示为集合R4
So this R4 means a
因此 这个R4是指
set of four-dimensional vectors.
一个四维向量的集合
Next let's talk about how to refer to the elements of the vector.
接下来让我们来谈谈如何引用向量的元素
We are going to use the notation
我们将使用符号
yi to refer to
yi来代表
the ith element of the
向量y的第i个元素
vector y. So if y
所以 如果这个向量是y
is this vector, y subscript i is the ith element.
那么y下标i 则表示它的第i个元素
So y1 is the
所以y1表示第一个元素
first element,four sixty, y2
is equal to the second element,
y2表示第二个元素
two thirty two -there's the first.
There's the second.
这是第二个元素
Y3 is equal to
还有y3等于
315 and so on, and
315 等等
only y1 through y4 are
只有y1至y4是有意义的
defined consistency 4-dimensional vector.
因为这定义的是一个四维向量
Also it turns out that
此外 事实上
there are actually 2 conventions
有两种方法来表达
for how to index into a
某个向量中某个索引
vector and here they are.
是这两种
Sometimes, people will use
有时候 人们会使用
one index and sometimes zero index factors.
1-索引 有时候用0-索引
So this example on the left
因此 左边这个例子
is a one in that
是一个1-索引向量
specter where the element
它的元素写作
we write is y1, y2, y3, y4.
y1 y2 y3 y4
And this example in the right
而右边这个向量
is an example of a zero index
是0-索引的一个例子
factor where we start
我们的索引
the indexing of the elements from zero.
从下标0开始
So the elements go from a zero up to y three.
因此 元素从y0至y3
And this is a bit like the
这有点像
arrays of some primary languages
一些初级语言中的数组
where the arrays can either
数组是从1开始
be indexed starting from one.
排序的
The first element of an
数组的第一个元素
array is sometimes a Y1,
一般时从y1开始
this is sequence notation I guess,
这是表示序列的符号
and sometimes it's zero index
有时是从0开始排序
depending on what programming language you use.
这取决于你用??什么编程语言
So it turns out that in
所以 事实上
most of math, the one
在数学中
index version is more
1-索引的情况比较多
common For a lot
而对于很多
of machine learning applications, zero index
机器学习的应用问题来说
vectors gives us a more convenient notation.
0-索引向量为我们提供了一个更方便的符号表达
So what you should usually
所以你通常应该
do is, unless otherwised specified,
做的是 除非特别指定
you should assume we are using one index vectors.
你应该默认我们使用的是1-索引法表示向量
In fact, throughout the rest
在本课程的后面所有
of these videos on linear algebra
关于线性代数的视频中
review, I will be using one index vectors.
我都将使用1-索引法表示向量
But just be aware that
但你要明白
when we are talking about machine learning
当我们谈论到机器学习的
applications, sometimes I will
应用问题时
explicitly say when we
如果我们需要使用0-索引向量的话
need to switch to, when we
我会明确地告诉你
need to use the zero index
我们什么时候换成
vectors as well.
使用0-索引表达
Finally, by convention, usually
最后 按照惯例
when writing matrices and vectors,
通常在书写矩阵和向量时
most people will use upper
大多数人会使用大写字母
case to refer to matrices.
来表示矩阵
So we're going to use
因此 我们要使用
capital letters like
大写字母 如
A, B, C, you know,
A B C
X, to refer to matrices,
X 来表示矩阵
and usually we'll use lowercase,
而通常我们会使用小写字母
like a, b, x, y,
像a b x y
to refer to either numbers,
来表示数字
or just raw numbers or scalars or to vectors.
或是原始的数字 或标量 或向量
This isn't always true but
这是实际的使用习惯
this is the more common
我们也经常看到
notation where we use
使用小写字母y
lower case "Y" for referring
来表示向量
to vector and we usually
但我们平时
use upper case to refer to a matrix.
是用大写字母来表示矩阵
So, you now know what are matrices and vectors.
所以 你现在知道了什么是矩阵和向量
Next, we'll talk about some
接下来 我们将继续讨论关于它们一些内容
of the things you can do with them